<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>M. Duncan | Designer, web developer, business owner</title>
    <description>I&#39;m M. Duncan: a designer, web developer, and small business owner</description>
    <link>http://mduncan.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://mduncan.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 07:55:18 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 07:55:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Zero Investor Business Plan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are many books, articles, and websites that explain how to write a business plan. Most tell you to follow their advice on what investors will want to see and plan accordingly. And if you want to start a small business, they say focus on a local bank instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example from one &lt;a href=&quot;http://gsl.mit.edu/media/programs/india-bms-summer-2013/materials/how-to-write-a-great-business-plan.pdf&quot;&gt;Harvard Business Review article&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If you want to speak the language of investors and also make sure you have asked yourself the right questions before setting out on the most daunting journey of a businessperson’s career—I recommend basing your business plan on the framework that follows.” &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their assumption is that your business will need significant funding. By following their instructions, you can be sure that your plan will serve a very narrow purpose. You might not use it beyond the funding phase. It will have boring section titles like ‘executive summary’ and ‘personnel plan.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are a lot of different ways to write a business plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I wouldn’t want outside funding to start my design business. So I had to rethink the whole point of my business plan. While the books and articles offered a lot of good advice,&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; I had to write for a different audience: me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t focus on investors or the bank. Instead, I made a resource that I can reference again and again. It’s something I would look forward to actually using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan includes several things that aren’t often mentioned in books or articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client personas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent time creating profiles, or personas, for the different types of clients I hope to work with. I used the same personas again when I designed a brand identity and website for my business. And again when I created an editorial strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Editorial and content strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing and talking about my business is a big part of attracting clients. I spent a lot of time creating an editorial calendar and setting goals to post to my website at least twice monthly. I also worked on a content strategy that I’ll refer to on a variety of business projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Milestones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read about milestones in &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/product/creating-business-plans-hbr-20-minute-manager-series/16998E-KND-ENG&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creating Business Plans&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This is one recommendation I gladly took. But this is the only book or article that mentioned anything like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A milestone plan gives your readers a timeline for the creation of a successful business. Develop an ambitious schedule that you can meet, while still giving yourself room to handle unexpected problems that may slow you down….Use generic dates, such as “month six” or “year one” rather than actual dates.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milestones aren’t calendar events, they are only for large and important events. I reference my milestones spreadsheet weekly. It’s incredibly useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best business plans are purpose built. They address the needs of the business owner. Investors may not be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m not looking for investors, I documented implementation details that make self-funding possible. I planned to start as soon as I could with resources that I had available. My business plan, written for me instead of some mythical investor, reflects this strategy. I reference parts of it all the time. By broadening the scope, I’ve created a living document that’s vital to my day to day work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Typical business writing hyperbole. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I agree that a good business plan requires asking the right questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2016 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://mduncan.me/business-plans/2016/08/07/a-zero-investor-business-plan.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mduncan.me/business-plans/2016/08/07/a-zero-investor-business-plan.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>business-plans</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Before I Write a Business Plan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Good business plans take time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the work is thinking, researching, writing, and revising. A business plan should be easy to implement and understand. It should build confidence in an idea. But it shouldn’t be long or complicated. Careful editing takes considerable time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process can take months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if your business plan doesn’t build confidence in your idea? It might not. You’ve done all the work, the hours of revision, and your idea has holes. Maybe it’s not the right time or place, or you’ve made too many assumptions about the industry or market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A business plan should reveal irreparable flaws; that’s its job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After considering its flaws, you may decide to abandon the idea. While okay, spending months on an idea that goes nowhere  isn’t the most efficient use of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I take the time to write a business plan, I spend an afternoon answering the questions below. They help me uncover flaws before I get too far. While they don’t guarantee a great business plan, they do reduce the risk of it ending up in the trash. When I’m done, I know if it’s an idea worth pursuing. If it’s not, I’ve only spent an afternoon working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The questions I work through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is the product or service? Who are the customers? How can I simplify the idea? Or, how can I expand it? How can I present a new or unique take on the product or service? What one-thing will this business be known for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start by simplifying the idea. It’s okay to think big, but I keep big ideas in a notebook for later. I’m looking for an idea that’s easy to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good businesses focus on doing one thing well. They are built around a simple idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What problem does the product or service solve for customers? How can I reach customers? Is accessing them affordable or expensive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I think about customer needs. The business &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; solve a problem. These questions prompt me to consider the relationship between what the business will do and what people need or expect from the product or service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think about my access to customers. I avoid markets where access is difficult, expensive, or tightly controlled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What industry will this business be part of? Is it large and growing? Who are the top competitors? What are their weaknesses? What experience do I have in this industry? Is industry and market data readily available? If so, from what sources? What experts can I talk to about this industry or market? What are niche areas in this market?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my business decisions will be informed by industry and market data. I need to know what’s available. And I need to think critically about the quality of that data.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also research niche areas in the market.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; This gives me clues about how I can narrow the business idea further. But I’m careful to avoid niches that are trendy. Trends, by nature, do not offer a stable foundation to build a business on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is the estimated cost to produce the product or service? Is the profit margin low or high? What will the estimated minimum start up costs be? Estimate how many months it will take to reach positive cash flow.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; How much money do I need to support myself for three months? For one year?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I charge for my product or service depends on how much I need to make a comfortable living. I also plan a financial buffer of at least three months. My goal is to reach positive cash flow during that period. And the buffer helps me cover living expenses while I get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If positive cash flow seems unlikely in the first 3-6 months, I need to rethink the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At minimum, how many employees will I need at start up? What pieces of equipment are essential? Can I do without physical space? If so, for how long? Is the business dependent on other people? Who? How many hours per week can I devote to this business?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I look for ways to reduce dependencies. Some equipment will be essential. Sometimes people need to be hired right away. But if I can do without it at the start, I will. Starting the business will be easier, and cost less, with fewer dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my responses might tell me this is a bad business idea. I know to move on if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It doesn’t solve an obvious problem.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There isn’t enough industry or market data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Positive cash flow seems unlikely&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is too dependent on other people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, however, I’m satisfied with all of my answers, I’m ready to start a business plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Who conducted the study, using what methods? What are their biases?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Niche Market, Wikipedia.org &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niche_market&quot;&gt;&amp;#8618;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Cash Flow, Wikipedia.org &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cash_flow&quot;&gt;&amp;#8618;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2016 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://mduncan.me/business-plans/2016/08/07/before-I-write-a-business-plan.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mduncan.me/business-plans/2016/08/07/before-I-write-a-business-plan.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>business-plans</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
