<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>M. Duncan • Designer, Web Developer, Small Business Owner</title>
    <description>I'm M. Duncan: a Designer, Web Developer, and Small Business Owner</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 10:06:53 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 10:06:53 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pattern Naming Conventions in Web Design</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Unlike &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/CSS_Selectors&quot;&gt;CSS selectors&lt;/a&gt; – &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/Class_selectors&quot;&gt;classes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/ID_selectors&quot;&gt;ids&lt;/a&gt; – that no one except designers or developers see, some of us are exposing our &lt;a href=&quot;http://patternlab.io/&quot;&gt;design systems and their naming conventions&lt;/a&gt; to clients during projects. Names of design elements are exposed in a way that they weren’t before. But do names really matter to our clients?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve spent time working with any type of complex system, you know that naming things is important. Relationships and hierarchies are expressed through names. If &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naming_convention_(programming)&quot;&gt;naming conventions&lt;/a&gt; don’t work or aren’t easy to follow, our understanding of the system falls apart. And that makes it hard to use and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattern based design is an attempt a systematizing the design and front-end development of websites. In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://atomicdesign.bradfrost.com/&quot;&gt;Atomic Design&lt;/a&gt; system naming conventions are an attempt to make the structure of the system more understandable. Single HTML elements are atoms, groups of elements are molecules, and sections are organisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works OK in practice. But I’ve found from experience that some clients struggle with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://atomicdesign.bradfrost.com/chapter-2/&quot;&gt;abstraction&lt;/a&gt;. It can also be difficult for me to explain and a time consuming part of a meeting that we’d both like to keep short and to-the-point. My clients have mostly been concerned with the larger parts of the system: templates and pages, sometimes sections. But they’re mostly underwhelmed reviewing block level elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I don’t use abstract naming conventions or even expose them to lower-level patterns other than font choice and sizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have my own light-weight pattern library tool. While inspired by Atomic Design and Pattern Lab, it’s got a smaller footprint. Rather than abstract names at the top level of the system – atoms, molecules, organisms – I use more literal names. My top-level pattern categories are: elements, blocks, and sections. This naming convention is an attempt at more semantic naming. ‘Elements’ for example, correspond to basic HTML elements like ‘&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;’. Content blocks are just ‘blocks’. And sections are . . . ‘sections.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I spend a little bit of time going over how I work with clients, I’m not that concerned with making sure they get the metaphor. I’d rather spend the limited time I have to get feedback on looking at the things they want to see in a context that’s familiar to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing about designing and developing with modular systems is their flexibility. It’s easy to use the underlying principles of something like Atomic Design but adapt them for the types of projects you work on. Look at the variety of systems out there: &lt;a href=&quot;http://patternlab.io/&quot;&gt;Pattern Lab&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lightningdesignsystem.com/&quot;&gt;Lightning Design System&lt;/a&gt;, MailChimp’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://ux.mailchimp.com/patterns&quot;&gt;Pattern Library&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re considering a pattern based approach to front-end design, don’t feel like you need to be locked into a specific tool. And it’s really not too difficult to develop your own.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/pattern-naming-conventions</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/pattern-naming-conventions</guid>
        
        
        <category>patterns</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Content Inventory and Pattern Vocabularies in Web Design</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of a web design project, it’s common to inventory content from the existing site. During a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/content-inventory.html&quot;&gt;typical inventory&lt;/a&gt; I catalog page titles, urls, author, owner, and metadata in a big spreadsheet. It’s a good way to survey the content and figure out what areas need work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But inventories can be doubly useful if you use a pattern based design methodology.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good opportunity to start thinking about what design patterns are needed on the new site. I’ve added additional columns to my inventory spreadsheet template for pattern names, categories, and descriptions. When I review and audit the inventory I look at the existing site for elements and sections that are similar or repeated often. Things to note, particularly in sites that weren’t built with patterns in mind, include sidebars, buttons, calls to action, or any similar elements that I see over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also starting to think about vocabulary. What patterns need unique names and how do I classify them? This taxonomy – the pattern names and their classification – will form the basis of a pattern library later in the design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ![Inventory Pattern Vocabulary](/images/assets/posts/inventory-pattern-vocab.png){:width=&quot;500px&quot;} --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/assets/posts/inventory-pattern-vocab2.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;meta small-caption&quot;&gt;
      Additional columns added for pattern planning: pattern (name), category, and description. Also, there were no heading tags so I've made a note to correct them in the new site architecture.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My HTML, CSS, and front-end JavaScript are all created to address needs cataloged during this early inventory. It’s a great place to start whether you use &lt;a href=&quot;http://patternlab.io/&quot;&gt;Pattern Lab&lt;/a&gt; or your own system, like I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://styleguides.io/&quot;&gt;Style guides&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://patternlab.io/&quot;&gt;Pattern Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ux.mailchimp.com/patterns/about&quot;&gt;Mailchimp's pattern library&lt;/a&gt;, are all different ways of approaching one methodology. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/content-inventory-and-pattern-vocabularies</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/content-inventory-and-pattern-vocabularies</guid>
        
        
        <category>ux</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Year In Review: 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;2016 was a big set up year for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on starting a side business selling design services and got ready to take on some clients. I &lt;em&gt;only just&lt;/em&gt; finished everything by the end of the year – and I really had to stretch myself to get it done. But I’m happy to note that I’ll be taking clients in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a quick list of what I did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Switched departments at work, from Software Development to Marketing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changed job titles, from Front-end Developer to User Experience Designer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went to Web Design Day in Pittsburgh, a great conference&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Registered my business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Completed my business plan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launched my website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Landed my first client&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Almost bought a house&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work I changed my job title to User Experience designer allowing me to focus more fully on research, strategy, analytics, and A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a side business while working full-time has been a challenge. More often than not I’m working early in the morning, at night, and on weekends. But I’m committed to making it work and I don’t plan on keeping these hours forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also spent a lot of time creating processes and workflows to make client work more efficient. I’m already a process driven person, but these will help while I balance working a day job with managing a side business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to 2017, I’ll launch a couple of projects that allow me to do more public design work. I can’t say much now, but most of them will be announced and then written about here in the next couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/year-in-review-2016</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/year-in-review-2016</guid>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Business Milestone Planning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In business book jargon milestones are major events in the life of a business. They are performance benchmarks like “break-even” or big projects like “launch the website.” Identifying and documenting milestones before starting a business is a milestone plan. It gives you a roadmap to follow while you go about the daily task of running your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to milestone planning by &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/&quot;&gt;Harvard Business Review’s&lt;/a&gt; book &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/product/creating-business-plans-hbr-20-minute-manager-series/16998E-KND-ENG&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creating Business Plans&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. My milestone plan is part of my business plan, but it can be used independently too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A milestone plan gives readers a timeline for the creation of a successful business…Include only major events (not each individual step) and choose milestones that can be clearly defined and easily measured…Use generic dates, such as “month six” or “year one,” rather than actual dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows major events taking place in one month increments starting when the business opens. It’s designed to be easy to show potential investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My business plan, however, is mostly reference material for me – &lt;a href=&quot;http://mduncan.me/a-zero-investor-business-plan&quot;&gt;a guide I use to help me run my business&lt;/a&gt;. So, my milestone plan also serves this purpose and required some modification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A timeline is a static graphic that’s difficult to change. Instead of a timeline I use a spreadsheet. I keep mine in Google Drive where I can make changes from any of my devices. My milestone plan isn’t set in stone – things inevitably come up – so it’s important to be able to move events and goals around and stay flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to tracking when milestones will be completed, I’ve added two other parameters. I also track status – not started, in progress, and completed – and the quarter when I plan to work on it. These new parameters let me use my milestone plan as a productivity tool too. I check it weekly and use it to make sure I’m on schedule to accomplish larger goals throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what it looks like, if you’re curious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/assets/posts/milestones-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Milestone spreadsheet&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/business-milestone-planning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/business-milestone-planning</guid>
        
        
        <category>business</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Zero Investor Business Plan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are many books, articles, and websites that explain how to write a business plan. Most tell you to follow their advice on what investors will want to see and plan accordingly. And if you want to start a small business, they say focus on a local bank instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example from one &lt;a href=&quot;http://gsl.mit.edu/media/programs/india-bms-summer-2013/materials/how-to-write-a-great-business-plan.pdf&quot;&gt;Harvard Business Review article&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you want to speak the language of investors and also make sure you have asked yourself the right questions before setting out on the most daunting journey of a businessperson’s career—I recommend basing your business plan on the framework that follows. &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their assumption is that your business will need significant funding. By following their instructions, you can be sure that your plan will serve a very narrow purpose. You might not use it beyond the funding phase. It will have boring section titles like ‘executive summary’ and ‘personnel plan.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are a lot of different ways to write a business plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I wouldn’t want outside funding to start my design business. So I had to rethink the whole point of my business plan. While the books and articles offered a lot of good advice,&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; I had to write for a different audience: me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t focus on investors or the bank. Instead, I made a resource that I can reference again and again. It’s something I would look forward to actually using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan includes several things that aren’t often mentioned in books or articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;client-personas&quot;&gt;Client personas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent time creating profiles, or personas, for the different types of clients I hope to work with. I used the same personas again when I designed a brand identity and website for my business. And again when I created an editorial strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;editorial-and-content-strategy&quot;&gt;Editorial and content strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing and talking about my business is a big part of attracting clients. I spent a lot of time creating an editorial calendar and setting goals to post to my website at least twice monthly. I also worked on a content strategy that I’ll refer to on a variety of business projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;milestones&quot;&gt;Milestones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read about milestones in &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/product/creating-business-plans-hbr-20-minute-manager-series/16998E-KND-ENG&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creating Business Plans&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This is one recommendation I gladly took. But this is the only book or article that mentioned anything like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A milestone plan gives your readers a timeline for the creation of a successful business. Develop an ambitious schedule that you can meet, while still giving yourself room to handle unexpected problems that may slow you down….Use generic dates, such as “month six” or “year one” rather than actual dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milestones aren’t calendar events, they are only for large and important events. I reference my milestones spreadsheet weekly. It’s incredibly useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best business plans are purpose built. They address the needs of the business owner. Investors may not be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m not looking for investors, I documented implementation details that make self-funding possible. I planned to start as soon as I could with resources that I had available. My business plan, written for me instead of some mythical investor, reflects this strategy. I reference parts of it all the time. By broadening the scope, I’ve created a living document that’s vital to my day to day work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Typical business writing hyperbole. &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I agree that a good business plan requires asking the right questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2016 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/a-zero-investor-business-plan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/a-zero-investor-business-plan</guid>
        
        
        <category>business-plans</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Before I Write a Business Plan</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Good business plans take time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the work is thinking, researching, writing, and revising. A business plan should be easy to implement and understand. It should build confidence in an idea. But it shouldn’t be long or complicated. Careful editing takes considerable time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process can take months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if your business plan doesn’t build confidence in your idea? It might not. You’ve done all the work, the hours of revision, and your idea has holes. Maybe it’s not the right time or place, or you’ve made too many assumptions about the industry or market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A business plan should reveal irreparable flaws; that’s its job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After considering its flaws, you may decide to abandon the idea. While okay, spending months on an idea that goes nowhere  isn’t the most efficient use of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I take the time to write a business plan, I spend an afternoon answering the questions below. They help me uncover flaws before I get too far. While they don’t guarantee a great business plan, they do reduce the risk of it ending up in the trash. When I’m done, I know if it’s an idea worth pursuing. If it’s not, I’ve only spent an afternoon working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The questions I work through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is the product or service? Who are the customers? How can I simplify the idea? Or, how can I expand it? How can I present a new or unique take on the product or service? What one-thing will this business be known for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start by simplifying the idea. It’s okay to think big, but I keep big ideas in a notebook for later. I’m looking for an idea that’s easy to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good businesses focus on doing one thing well. They are built around a simple idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What problem does the product or service solve for customers? How can I reach customers? Is accessing them affordable or expensive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I think about customer needs. The business &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; solve a problem. These questions prompt me to consider the relationship between what the business will do and what people need or expect from the product or service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think about my access to customers. I avoid markets where access is difficult, expensive, or tightly controlled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What industry will this business be part of? Is it large and growing? Who are the top competitors? What are their weaknesses? What experience do I have in this industry? Is industry and market data readily available? If so, from what sources? What experts can I talk to about this industry or market? What are niche areas in this market?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my business decisions will be informed by industry and market data. I need to know what’s available. And I need to think critically about the quality of that data.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also research niche areas in the market.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; This gives me clues about how I can narrow the business idea further. But I’m careful to avoid niches that are trendy. Trends, by nature, do not offer a stable foundation to build a business on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is the estimated cost to produce the product or service? Is the profit margin low or high? What will the estimated minimum start up costs be? Estimate how many months it will take to reach positive cash flow.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; How much money do I need to support myself for three months? For one year?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I charge for my product or service depends on how much I need to make a comfortable living. I also plan a financial buffer of at least three months. My goal is to reach positive cash flow during that period. And the buffer helps me cover living expenses while I get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If positive cash flow seems unlikely in the first 3-6 months, I need to rethink the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At minimum, how many employees will I need at start up? What pieces of equipment are essential? Can I do without physical space? If so, for how long? Is the business dependent on other people? Who? How many hours per week can I devote to this business?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I look for ways to reduce dependencies. Some equipment will be essential. Sometimes people need to be hired right away. But if I can do without it at the start, I will. Starting the business will be easier, and cost less, with fewer dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my responses might tell me this is a bad business idea. I know to move on if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It doesn’t solve an obvious problem.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There isn’t enough industry or market data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Positive cash flow seems unlikely&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is too dependent on other people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, however, I’m satisfied with all of my answers, I’m ready to start a business plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;meta&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Who conducted the study, using what methods? What are their biases?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niche_market&quot;&gt;Niche Market, Wikipedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cash_flow&quot;&gt;Cash Flow, Wikipedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2016 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/before-I-write-a-business-plan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/before-I-write-a-business-plan</guid>
        
        
        <category>business-plans</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
